Overview Guide to the New-York Historical Society Records 1804-2018 NYHS-RG Archives
New-York Historical Society
- NYHS-RG 15. Collection accession registers (1841-1962, 2002)
  The New-York Historical Society collections accession registers include records from 1841-1962 concerning donations to and purchases for the institution. It is unknown how complete the records are. Museum objects were entered to the registers until the early 1940s. Library acquisitions, including books, manuscripts, photographs, maps, and Print Room material, were entered to the registers until 1962.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection Accession Registers.
- NYHS-RG 16. Bequests, gifts & related matters (1852-1992)
  The New-York Historical Society bequests, gifts & related matters record group (NYHS-RG 16) primarily includes records concerning estates in which N-YHS was named as a beneficiary. Most of these instances resulted in N-YHS receiving museum objects, manuscripts, books, or other items or a financial legacy. The record group also includes files of some donations of objects and funds from donors during their lifetimes, as well as some purchases. The record group includes files on some of the most important patrons and objects in N-YHS's history. The record group is restricted in part, but generally records from 1960 and earlier are available.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Bequests, Gifts & Related Matters Record Group.
- NYHS-RG 17. Publication editorial records (1939-2000, 2009)
  The New-York Historical Society publication editorial records include material related to publications produced by N-YHS from the 1940s to the early 1990s, with some later documents. Much of the record group includes the files of N-YHS's Editorial Department, which existed from about 1942 to 1980, and relates to the editorial work for articles proposed and written for the organization's journal, the Quarterly. The files also include editorial records for some of the books published by N-YHS, especially George C. Groce and David H. Wallace's Dictionary of Artists in America (1957), for which there is extensive correspondence and research notes. The record group also includes the papers presented at a series of six conferences on historical themes sponsored by N-YHS and organized by historian William Pencak from 1983 to 1988, along with the editorial files for the four volumes co-edited by Pencak based on the conference proceedings. Other principal correspondents include editors Charles E. Baker and Kathleen Luhrs, designer Klaus Gemming, members of N-YHS's Publications Committee, and authors William Sawitzky, Susan Clay Sawitzky, Mary Bartlett Cowdrey, Paul H. Downing, Irwin Cortelyou, Rita Gottesman, and others.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Publication Editorial Records
- NYHS-RG 18. Board of Trustees records (1939-1959)
  Scope and Contents
  The New-York Historical Society Board of Trustee records primarily include the materials related to Board meetings, including agendas, minutes, committee reports, various documents distributed at the meetings, and some working files from 1939 forward. Records through 1959 are open for research; records after 1959 are currently restricted.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Board of Trustees Records
- NYHS-RG 19. Librarian Dorothy C. Barck records (1921-1954)
  The New-York Historical Society Librarian Dorothy C. Barck record group primarily contains correspondence between Barck and patrons or members of N-YHS concerning research inquiries. The correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing letters from many amateur historians and genealogists. Some correspondence relates to Barck's duties as Editor, as head of the library, and to her involvement with professional organizations of librarians and archivists. The record group also includes annual reports, forms, statistics, offers from book dealers and sellers, and logbooks of reference inquiries.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Librarian Dorothy C. Barck Records
- NYHS-RG 20. Museum Department records (1765, 1830-2018)
  The New-York Historical Society Museum Department records include curatorial, collections management, exhibitions, outgoing loans, administrative, and object files created by museum staff. The bulk of the records range from the 1970s into the early twenty-first century, though there is important earlier material, including acquisition and other documents concerning the John J. Audubon watercolors and the Henry Abbott Egyptian collection. The most extensive portions of the record group relate to exhibitions and loans, and those files are rich with checklists, images, loan documentation, publicity material, research files, comment books, wall texts and labels, design elements, budgets and funding requests, and other like matter. The curatorial and collection management files include documents concerning proposed exhibitions, general exhibition scheduling, research inquiries, offers of objects for accession, object surveys, recommendations to the Board Museum Collection Committee, conservation, and other museum matters. There are also many object images, especially for paintings and drawings.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Museum Department Records
- NYHS-RG 21. Library Department records (1815-2018)
  The New-York Historical Society Library Department records group includes a broad range of material related to the administration of the Library and its component sections, including the Reading Room, Manuscripts Department, Department of Prints, Photographs and Architecture (PPAC, often referred to as the Print Room), and the Conservation Lab. The subject matter spans the entire breadth of the Library's activities: acquisition of materials for the collection, curatorial and conservation surveys and assessments, collection inventorying and cataloging projects, in-house exhibitions and outgoing loans, and patron access and use of the collections.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Library Department Records
- NYHS-RG 23. Public programs and education records 1941-2014 (bulk, 1984-2004)
  The New-York Historical Society public programs and education records include files related to the creation, publicity, outreach, funding, management, and implementation of N-YHS's programs, principally for the years 1984-1992. Regular programming included, among other things, panel discussions, lectures, concerts, films, museum gallery tours, teacher/educator workshops, and special collaborations such as arts-in-education classes or programs for at-risk students.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Public Programs and Education Records
- NYHS-RG 24. Financial Records, 1837-2005 (bulk 1800s-1930s, 1980s-1993)
  Although the record group does not hold comprehensive records concerning N-YHS's financial history, there are several 19th century records (cash ledgers, mortgagee holdings documentation, bank books, etc.) that provide glimpses into N-YHS's early finances. Also there is extensive financial data (expenses, budgets, investments, etc.) for the late 1980s and early 1990s; though the timeframe is limited, it represents a period when N-YHS faced a severe fiscal crisis and so can provide insight into that pivotal moment in the organization's history. The record group also holds much information about many of N-YHS's special funds (e.g., Harper Fund) and the financial aspects of the Encyclopedia of New York City project.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Financial Records
- NYHS-RG 26. Museum Store records (1940s-2001, bulk 1980s-1992)
  The New-York Historical Society museum store records include documents related to the management of the store, development of its product lines, and marketing. The files include correspondence, sales catalogs, inventories, sales results, reproduction licensing, orders, and photographs of catalog items. There are also examples of some of the products sold at the store, especially small format items like postcards and greeting cards. The bulk of the material relates to the period 1985 to 1991.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Museum Store Records
- NYHS-RG 28. Audiovisual media records (1974-2002)
  The New-York Historical Society audiovisual media records primarily include videocassettes and audiocassettes from the late 1980s to early 1990s. N-YHS's lectures, panel discussions and concerts organized around the "Why History?" theme (1990-92) and programs connected to the bicentennial of the U.S. Constitution (1987) are especially well-documented, though many other presentations in video or audio format are also included. Audiotapes include training for docents and N-YHS education staff concerning particular N-YHS exhibitions and gallery installations. The record group is currently restricted because of the lack of appropriate playback equipment and the fragility of the tapes.
  Click here to link to the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Audiovisual Media Record Group